Guide to the John Lounsbury Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Lounsbury papers
1813-1895
MS 1300
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
The papers consist of medical notes, notebooks, school materials, prescriptions, and poetry of John and Mary Lounsbury.
Lounsbury, John, 1809-1895
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Lounsbury was born on August 16, 1809, in Bethany, Connecticut. He prepared for college at Wilbraham Academy, and graduated from Yale Medical School in 1837. For a short time, he practiced medicine in Hamden, before moving to Oxford, Connecticut, in 1840. He specialized in chronic diseases. In April 1843, Lounsbury married Mary Church, who had been a teacher in New York and Connecticut. He was an advocate of Episcopal parochial schools for girls and attempted to establish one in Oxford. Throughout his life, Lounsbury enjoyed writing poetry. He died on April 6, 1895, in Oxford, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of medical notes, notebooks, school materials, prescriptions, and poetry of John and Mary Lounsbury.
Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Poems; Lounsbury, John, 1809-1895
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, poems, and other material, 1813-1838 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to John Lounsbury and Mary Church, 1839-1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1874, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Mary Church in New York to her brother, n.y. May 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arithmetic book for Mary Church, probably while attending Newburgh Academy, Circa 1824-1826 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Handwriting lessons] with bills on reverse, 1826 November 10, November 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bookkeeping exercises, Wesleyan Academy, Wilbraham, Massachusetts, 1829-1833 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Andrews, Charles C., "Geographical Exercises for Infant Schools..." New York, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Elements of Geography by S.W.S. for the Use of the Public Primary Schools New York", 1833 January (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Primary school documents and lessons, Circa 1835-1836 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Poetry and educational documents, 1836-1837, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Documents relating to education and poetry (often about education or children), 1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Drawings and documents on primary education and Mary Church's career as a teacher, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notebook with lessons for young children and poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Lesson on Infant Schools", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lessons on light, botany, paper, and architecture, and various hymns and poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Medical journal containing medical documents, Circa 1838-Circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notebook with medical notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Medical notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "A Concise and General View of the Several Pneumonitides", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Prescriptions, treatments, formulas, medical writings, and other documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Documents relating to the treatment of various diseases and John Lounsbury business cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hymns, 1831, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Poetry and other writings, often written on scraps of other documents or envelopes, Circa 1836-Circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Matrimony" poem, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Admission tickets to lectures at the Medical Institution of Yale College and related documents, 1834-1836 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, 1873 and undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Soda Water Apparatus for 1879 Manufactured by John Matthews" catalogue (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Marriage notice for third sabbath of March, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Resolutions, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)